{"tossups": [{"question": "This civilization\u2019s Mehrgarh period provided early evidence of animal herding. Chickens may have been bred for religious cockfights under this civilization. The Great Granary and the ancient world\u2019s first public bath were built by this civilization at the Mound of the Dead. This civilization was centered around the Sindh province of Pakistan and included cities like Harappa and Mohenjo-Daro. For the point, name this Bronze Age civilization, named for a river valley.", "answer": "<b> Indus</b> (River) Valley Civilization", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this\u201cenlightened despot\u201d of Prussia.", "answer": "<b> Frederick the Great</b> (accept<b> Frederick II</b>; prompt on Frederick)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Thomas Truxtun engaged two ships from this country while commanding the<em> Constellation</em>. The U.S. signed the 1800 Treaty of Mortefontaine with this country, ending the Quasi-War. A statesman from this country who participated in the American Revolutionary War was nicknamed \u201cCitizen.\u201d A marquis from this country commanded a contingent of troops at Yorktown. For the point, name this home country of Citizen Genet and the Marquis de Lafayette.", "answer": "<b> France</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In one of this man\u2019s novels, a general is thought to be the \u201cbeast prophesied in the Apocalypse\u201d after his name is found to correspond to the number 666. This author, whose<em> Sevastopol Sketches</em> were set during the Crimean War, wrote about Pierre Bezhukov watching the Battle of Borodino during Napoleon\u2019s invasion of Russia. For the point, name this Russian author of<em> War and Peace</em>.", "answer": "Leo<b> Tolstoy</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Former DNC chair Howard Dean served as governor of this state in the 1990s. A senator from this state served as mayor of its city of Burlington and lost the 2016 Democratic nomination for president to Hillary Clinton. For the point, name this home state of Senator Bernie Sanders.", "answer": "<b> Vermont</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "This event led to a trial where Kate Alterman\u2019s testimony was thrown out after she was accused of memorizing her account. Max Steuer helped defend Max Blanck and Isaac Harris from blame after this event, which inspired the creation of the ILGWU. Locked exits in the Asch building forced workers to jump from windows in, for the point, what 1911 industrial disaster at a garments factory in New York?", "answer": "<b> Triangle Shirtwaist</b> Factory fire", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was the target of a plot between his former mentee, Henri Cinq-Mars, and the comte de Soissons. On the \u201cDay of the Dupes,\u201d this man nearly lost power when Marie de Medici asked for his removal. This man successfully organized the capture of La Rochelle, a rebel stronghold, and led French diplomatic efforts for much of the Thirty Years\u2019 War. He was replaced by Jules Mazarin. For the point, name this chief advisor of Louis XIII, a cardinal who was nicknamed the \u201cRed Eminence.\u201d", "answer": "Cardinal<b> Richelieu</b> (or Armand Jean du<b> Plessis</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "After being damaged in a fire in the artist\u2019s studio, the first version of this painting was destroyed in a World War II bombing raid almost 100 years later. A figure in red who may have been a woman and a man of African descent are among those portrayed in this painting, in which a flag is being hoisted by James Monroe. A plot to secretly attack a group of celebrating Hessians is depicted in, for the point, what Emmanuel Leutze painting of a rowboat carrying members of the Continental Army?", "answer": "<b> Washington Crossing the Delaware</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The losing side of this battle attempted to gain air superiority in Operation Baseplate and used a rare night time paratrooper raid during Operation Stosser. During this battle, George Patton claimed he could relieve Bastogne in just 48 hours. One side in this battle launched an attack through the Ardennes Forest in an attempt to recapture Antwerp. For the point, name this 1944 battle named for the shape made in Nazi front lines.", "answer": "Battle of the<b> Bulge</b> (accept<b> Ardennes Counter-offensive</b> before \u201cArdennes\u201d is read; accept Operation<b> Watch on the Rhine</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Howard Florey and Ernst Chain employed a large group of girls at Oxford to grow this substance on the surfaces of bathtubs and other vessels before improved methods of growing it in submerged culture were developed. A British police officer with a face wound became the first patient treated with injections of this substance in 1941. An accidentally-uncovered Petri dish helped Alexander Fleming discover, for the point, what mold that became a massively successful antibiotic in the mid-20th century?", "answer": "<b> penicillin</b>", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "This country is home to both the only known tree planted by Che Guevara and the oldest planted tree known to man. A \u201cfortress in the sky,\u201d Sigiriya, was built in this country, where Anula became the first woman to rule an Asian nation. A famous tooth relic of the Buddha is located in this country\u2019s city of Kandy. Adam\u2019s Bridge connects the mainland to, for the point, what island country where the Tamil Tigers fought a lengthy civil war in the Indian Ocean?", "answer": "<b> Sri Lanka</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This program was introduced in a speech that declared \u201cmillions cannot and shall not hope in vain.\u201dOne of this program\u2019s initiatives was ruled unconstitutional in the<em> Schechter Poultry</em> case. This program began with a bank holiday and the passing of the Glass-Steagall Act. The Tennessee Valley Authority was established as part of, for the point, what domestic program by Franklin Roosevelt that fought to end the Great Depression?", "answer": "<b> New Deal</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This dynasty was continued by Koxinga, who had fled to Taiwan after the success of Li Zicheng\u2019s rebellion. The Battle of Lake Poyang led to the establishment of this dynasty under its first emperor, Hongwu. This dynasty built the Forbidden City and brought back giraffes after sending admiral Zheng He on a series of voyages. It eventually fell to Manchu invasions. For the point, name this last ethnically Han Chinese dynasty, which fell in 1644.", "answer": "<b> Ming</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Thirty-six of this monarch\u2019s advisors were executed after taking part in a conspiracy known as the Affair of the Poisons. Foreign enemies of this man formed the Grand Alliance to oppose his expansionism, and this king was targeted domestically in the Fronde revolt. This man revoked the Edict of Nantes with the Edict of Fontainebleau, ending toleration for Huguenots, and he defended his policies by declaring \u201cI am the state.\u201d For the point, name this despotic French monarch known as the Sun King.", "answer": "<b> Louis XIV</b> [14] (prompt on the Sun King before mentioned; prompt on Louis)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "On this river, Union forces under Andrew Foote and John Pope captured the strategic Island Number 10. The Old River Control Structure diverts some of this river\u2019s water into the neighboring Atchafalaya River, before this river flows through the \u201cCrescent City.\u201d The New Madrid [MAH-drid] Earthquake, which drew support for Tecumseh, caused this river to flow backwards. For the point, name this river that travels past New Orleans into the Gulf of Mexico.", "answer": "<b> Mississippi</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This leader was forced to resign after facing an internal party challenge from Michael Heseltine. James Callaghan was replaced by this leader after facing the \u201cwinter of discontent.\u201d The Poll Tax riots began after this politician instituted the unpopular Community Charge. After removing free dairy products for schoolkids, this leader was disparaged as a \u201cmilk snatcher.\u201d For the point, name this conservative Prime Minister of the UK, known as the \u201cIron Lady.\u201d", "answer": "Margaret<b> Thatcher</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This politician declared \u201cwe stand at Armageddon and we battle for the Lord\u201d to spur on his New Nationalism movement. Progressives rallied under this man after the president fired Forest Bureau head Gifford Pinchot. This third party candidate split votes with William Howard Taft, allowing Woodrow Wilson to take victory in the Election of 1912. For the point, name this founder of the Bull Moose party, a former trust-busting president.", "answer": "<b> T</b>heodore (or<b> T</b>eddy)<b> Roosevelt</b> (prompt on Roosevelt)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The composer of this work noted that \u201cJoy follows sorrow\u201d when he explained why this work ends in C major despite its<em> Allegro con brio</em> first movement being in C minor. The Morse code for the letter V coincidentally mimics the rhythm of this work\u2019s primary motif, leading this piece to be a Allied symbol for \u201cVictory\u201d in World War II. For the point, name this symphony by Ludwig van Beethoven that opens with an iconic \u201cshort-short-short-long\u201d motif.", "answer": "Ludwig van<b> Beethoven</b>\u2019s<b> 5</b>th<b> Symphony</b> (\u201dsymphony\u201d not needed after it is read;\u201cBeethoven\u201d not needed after it is read)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This event led to the banning of the RSS party for the first time and the false arrest of Vinayak Savarkar. A young girl tried to stop this event\u2019s perpetrator by saying \u201cBapu is already late.\u201d This event took place as its target went to the Birla House for morning prayer. The prime minister declared \u201cthe light has gone out from our lives\u201d after Nathuram Godse carried out this event. For the point, name this January 30, 1948 event in which a non-violent Indian independence leader was killed.", "answer": "<b> assassination</b> (or<b> murder</b>,<b> shooting</b>, etc.) of<b> M</b>ohandas<b> Gandhi</b> (or of<b> M</b>ahatma<b> Gandhi</b>) (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This route was preceded by the similar York Factory Express, which carried fur traders of Hudson\u2019s Bay Company. Covered wagons could only be carried as far as Fort Hall along this route, which split off into the Mormon and Bozeman roads. Dysentery frequently plagued travelers on this trail as they moved from Independence, Missouri, to the Willamette Valley. For the point, name this 19th century trail that led settlers to the Pacific Northwest.", "answer": "<b> Oregon</b> Trail", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man rose to prominence after the Cleveland Massacre, in which he absorbed all of his competitors in the city.<em> McClure\u2019s</em> magazine helped expose the business practices of this man by publishing the work of muckraker Ida Tarbell. After adjustment for inflation, this man still stands as the richest American ever. The Sherman Antitrust Act created corporations like Chevron and Shell by breaking up a company founded by, for the point, what American industrialist who founded Standard Oil?", "answer": "John D.<b> Rockefeller</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was defeated for the first time after failing to capture the Alte Veste fortress from the forces of Albrecht von Wallenstein. Axel Oxenstierna ruled as chancellor after this man was fatally shot in a cavalry charge. After leading Protestant forces to victory at Breitenfeld, this man was killed at Lutzen. This \u201cLion of the North\u201d was succeeded by his daughter Christina Vasa. For the point, name this Swedish king in the Thirty Years\u2019 War.", "answer": "<b> Gustavus Adolphus</b> (accept<b> Gustav II</b> Adolf)", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}